[Music]
w
hello good evening good day everybody
and welcome to the 224th episode of the
ask abijit show I hope everybody is
doing great before we begin let's see
who all is there on the live chat let us
see uh we can see Shas Kar nwat ainka
dangra
pakari
Su uh J prit Singh NES gang G Rahul
Mahajan Shri harar ner Matrix Jagdish
Mali GK Mukesh by Shri Hari Arjun again
geopolitical dub tanoy de sha ja abishek
Shasta goami saket katari Krishna goind
Alfred ragunath B Rai from the
surinamese Netherlands dungar Singh Chan
hello threat Ripper tagat Karan Karan
naat toan Chri NES prai Paul mahita
busetti truth Matrix vov
dangra Sunil chavare sakeet
katari hian Harel Shan jasman Raj Singh
Dr
Atul Mukesh From the Ashes adash Kumar
yadav Akash ba project smiling Buddha
thank you for the contribution
appreciate that Vidor abishek sastav Jo
Singh
jatar indis Swami EDI Tano beat Brawlers
sagur mavin hello adya Singh room card
and everybody else all right welcome to
everybody and thank you so much for
being on this live stream I can see some
more people janavi Amisha Shri Hari
Arjun and everybody else else right okay
so so I'm going to take questions that
you have asked in the comments and I'll
take some questions from the live chat
also so let's go let's begin what are
the questions that we have today lots of
questions as
always let's begin with something
different for a
change so this is by prai Paul and the
question is Elon Musk has reportedly
chosen the name Terminus for the first
city on Mars once Mars is successfully
colonized how do you think the US might
approach its governance will they claim
sovereignty over the planet and
Implement laws according to their
interests how might this shape
Humanity's approach to inhabiting Mars
and potentially other planets in the
future okay so uh what could be the the
approach of the United States towards
governing Mars that's an important
question that we have to consider today
and how could
we try and determine what this approach
could be like so we can look at past
history to see what's happened in the
past I mean we have never colonized
another planet in the past but in the
past let's say 500 years ago the
Europeans discovered the Americas
rediscovered the Americas after the
Viking the brief Viking uh period there
so the Europeans rediscovered the
Americas and they started colonizing the
Americas and immediately you found that
there were conflicts of interest the
span the Spanish had their agenda they
wanted to have the largest territory
possible the French wanted to grab
territory everybody wanted to grab
territory and everybody wanted the
territory and the resources for
themselves and you had Wars that
happened because of this uh So
eventually so initially when you have
just a handful of people on mars or the
moon it's going to be for all humanity
and all that stuff that's what they will
say we are doing this for Humanity but
eventually once you have a self-
sustaining Colony on Mar
s the question will arise about its
governance and at that point in time the
United States will most likely declare
that this is a US
Territory I mean it's it's a given
that's what's going to
happen and if the US is the only nation
that that is able to develop the ability
to reach Mars then they could claim that
Mars is a US possession the whole of the
planet it's
possible um and the same could apply to
the Moon so initially you would have a
US Territory on the moon and then you
may have a Chinese territory Russian
territory perhaps on the moon I'm not
sure if India even has any I mean India
has said that we will have humans on the
Moon by 2040 or something but it's all I
mean it's it's far away in the future
the Americans can send people to the
Moon in a couple of
years so the US will eventually claim
these territories as their own as its
own and even more important they will
decide who gets to go to Mars or the
moon and who doesn't get to go there
they will decide they will set the
criteria it's going to be mostly US
citizens and if if non- US citizens are
allowed to go there it's going to be
citizens of Nations that are closely
aligned with the US and and serve the US
geopolitical objectives so that's how
it's going to be and that's why it's
important that India Nations like India
do not get left behind in the Space Race
because eventually it's all about
control of
resources and uh the two or three
nations that will lead the world in
space exploration in the 21st
century are going to be the two or three
nations that control the world that lead
the world overall in everything so right
now it looks like India has the
government of India has no ambition when
it comes to space there are some small
space space programs going on there's
going to be a gagan program which is a
technology demonstrator of human space
flight which will happen in 25 26
probably 25 26 the first human space
flight um and this talk of an Indian
space station eventually in the
2030s and so on but India doesn't seem
to be very ambitious the government of
India doesn't seem to realize how
important space exploration is um and
space exploration is probably what will
transform the US from a mere superpower
to a hyper
power uh um yeah so that's how I see it
the US will eventually claim sovereignty
over all the territories it controls on
the moon and it may claim sovereignty
over the entirety of Mars if no other
nation is able to U develop the
technology to reach there so important
that other nations participate in the
space race and compete in the Space
Race abishek shast says will India act
on Bangladesh when Trump comes to
power look there are some people who who
imagine okay that uh when Once Trump
takes uh office in January J January
21st or something uh then India can will
be able to make certain policies that
it's not able to implement right now so
maybe India will be able to uh take C
take certain steps in Manipur that it's
not able to take right now maybe
something to do with Burma maybe
something in Bangladesh that's what lots
of people imagine that the US policy
towards India will certainly become
radically different once Trump comes to
power let's understand something US
foreign policy never changes whether
it's Trump whether it's Democrats in
power or the Republicans in power
whether it's Kamala and Joe Biden J
Biden or whether it's trump it makes no
difference so US policies towards India
will not change
significantly once Trump comes once once
uh Trump takes the oath of office
nothing major will happen the US US
policy to towards India visa Bangladesh
will remain exactly the same when it
comes to Manipur project K cooki land
for Christ will continue nothing will
change Trump will not be allowed to make
any major changes to un foreign policy
so when it comes to Bangladesh India and
the US will remain
adversaries and the US will continue to
take actions that will promote its
geopolitical interests in the
subcontinent so uh
so nothing will change when it comes to
Bangladesh once Trump comes to power
India won't be able to make any to do
anything that it's not able to do right
now nothing will
change okay questions about uh Burma
Myanmar so subhankar shubhankar says I
have heard the arakan Army has a has
total control of Myanmar Bangladesh
border and has conquered vast chunks of
territory in the raken state something
interesting brewing in our neighborhood
you think it's our doing or we're just
Spectators
again uh yes thank you Shankar and
mudgal C Miss says we have recently seen
the arakan Army being rumored to of
having captured about 270 square
kilometers of Bangladeshi territory we
also know that China and the US are the
main funders of the arakan army and we
are also aware uh of the fact that these
people are were highly Pro India
pre98 when we had their leaders arrested
in the andan nicobar could India be
behind this especially since we have
seen Mr D visiting China could it
perhaps be that India through the raw
has decided to get its hands dirty in
the matter or are we going to keep up
our roughly our highly timid foreign
policy um I have my doubts about the
Aran Army since the US and China won the
chiong region want these guys give the
give the captured land to the highest
bidder like the us or maybe China okay a
whole bunch of questions are being asked
over here okay first of all uh what is
this arakan Army
is is it being funded by the US and
China both look the US and China are not
Nations that cooperate in geopolitics
they are adversaries in
geopolitics so it's it's doesn't make
sense for the US and China to fund the
same uh Force doesn't make sense at all
so when it comes to the arakan
Army um it's an ethnonationalist group
based in the arakan province of Burma
the Rakin province Let's uh go to the
map since we are uh discussing this
matter let's put the map on the screen
where's the map here is the map so we're
talking about our neighborhood east of
India we talk about Myanmar so let's
quickly look at the extent of the raken
state Myanmar how large is it so that's
so here we have the the region that is
shaded in red that's outlined in red is
the arakan region the Rakin region as
you can see uh significant amount of the
significant portion of the Burma
Bangladesh border uh adjoins the arakan
state so the arakan Army is an
ethnonationalist group that is based out
of the Rakin State there's another group
which is called the uh arsa the which is
a rohinga organization it's a terrorist
group that has been murdering Hindus and
Buddhists and all that they're also
based out of the Rakin State now the
arakan
Army it's uh it's composed of people who
are actually arakan in ethnicity they
are
Buddhists they are not ringas so the so
the
rohinga arsa group and the arakan army
they are at loggerheads they are
adversaries and the ringas one could
imagine if one looks at it properly they
could probably be on the P role of the
West similar to the various cookie uh
terrorist groups Etc and Insurgent
groups and so on that operate in this
region um so the arakan
Army is has in the past been closely
aligned with
China okay and they are
Buddhists they their adversaries are the
ringas their adversaries you could say
are the
West uh directly or
indirectly now the let's take a look at
the last question over here um since the
US and China want the chiong region Etc
would want these guys give the captured
land to the highest bidder first of all
the arakan Army has not taken over
chagang the chattogram region the coxis
Bazar region they have not taken it over
they have simply established control of
the border and they have nibbled away at
some small parts of Bangladeshi
territory like thn Etc but historically
some of this could have been part of the
arakan region and why would they give up
their own land to foreigners who are
bidding for it you see when when a
terrorist group or or an Insurgent group
captures territory that is not that is
which is not its own ancestral Homeland
then they'll be okay to give it up to
the highest bidder to sell it to the
highest bitter but when you're defending
your own Homeland from foreigners why
would you sell it to somebody you won't
do that you're fighting for your own
selfdetermination and freedom right so
that we that is an important point we
have to consider now let's go back to
the map and understand uh what has
happened in the recent past so reports
have emerged so we looking at this
region okay let's zoom in
now so the arakan army seems to have
taken over
tnaf which is a city in this region in
the Bangladeshi City and other areas
they seem to have established control
over this region and as you can see that
kind of cuts off the Saint Martin's
Island from
Bangladesh if the situation
persists okay so that's an important and
interesting development that's happened
over here that is a setback for for the
Muhammad yunus regime there is a setback
for
Bangladesh uh the situation could be
fluid it it may have changed perhaps
maybe they may have taken over more
territory maybe less territory one also
hears that there are ships from Pakistan
that are going towards Bangladesh which
with large quantities of arms and
ammunition to bolster the Bangladeshi
Defense Forces military forces ability
to to fight off the arakan um the arakan
Army and so on so the situation is kind
of complex right
now but reports did come out that the
arakan Army took over that part of that
small part of Bangladesh and maybe if
the Bangladeshi government isn't able to
control the situation then things could
spread and the uh arakan Army's control
over Bangladesh territory could expand
right now could India be behind this is
the question that's being asked could
China be behind this what is going on
there are arakan Army was pro- China
wasn't it um could India and China be
doing a joint venture over here that's a
question so of late we have seen that
India and China are talking again there
has been some kind of a r rmo of kinds
of sorts between India and China U like
uh mdal C Miss mentioned Mr Ajit dual
was recently in Beijing which is a
highly unprecedented step uh so a lot is
happening seems to be happening behind
the scenes between India and China and
when it comes to the Myanmar to the
country of Myanmar we are witnessing
large scale foreign interference in
Myanmar Western interference and that is
something that's bad for India as well
as for China so it makes sense perhaps I
mean logically it makes sense for India
and CH China to cooperate in this in in
in stabilizing this region and ensuring
that Pro West elements don't take
control of this region of Burma like
what's happening in Bangladesh we don't
want that to happen in
Burma uh so it's possible that India and
China may be cooperating in this I don't
think we are spectators anymore Shankar
says uh do you think it's our doing or
do you think we just Spectators again I
don't think India is a spectator in this
region uh we know the see the Bangladesh
situation the Burma situation and the
Manipur situation are interconnected
interrelated these are not separate
issues it's all part of the overall same
Geo
geopolitical uh game right the the
Americans have this project K that they
want to create an artificial Christian
cookie Nation out of parts of Burma
Bangladesh and Myanmar and this was
first stated over a year ago by then
prime minister shik Hina which was an
incredible claim he made but we see that
happening in real time now so she was
absolutely right it's not some
conspiracy theory when the sitting prime
minister of a country makes the claim
and then we see it actually happening uh
so it makes sense for India and China to
cooperate here I don't think India is a
spectator anymore right now it may have
taken the government some time to take
action the government has been
completely silent on Manipur the Prime
Minister doesn't say a word okay
whatever but hopefully things are moving
in the right direction uh so uh it looks
like India and China could be uh
cooperating in this matter and maybe the
arakan Army is pro-india and pro-china
perhaps and they are Buddhist so so
culturally and civilization they have no
issue with India unlike the ringas or or
unlike the the modern day nation of
Bangladesh culturally culturally
civilization they are antagonistic to us
aren't they the arakan the Buddhists
they have no such issues with
India uh so yeah this is a situation
that's developing right now it's an
ongoing situation ation so let's keep an
eye on this and let's see how it how it
evolves Maybe by by next week so I'll
keep an eye on this and we'll we'll
discuss this this further is there any
other part of the question that I have
missed over
here yeah so the main point is that I
don't think the US is funding the arakan
Army the US has been funding most likely
the ringas and the cookies not the
Buddhists see the US it usually funds
organizations and groups that have an
allegiance or with with an abrahamic
religion it's very rare for them to fund
organizations with allegiances to
dharmic religions right so I don't think
the US is involved in this the Chinese
have no issues with dhic religions so
there you have
it okay next question Rohit pwar pwar
says very weak attempt to cover up
coward this why hasn't the Modi
government thrown out more than the
three more than three CR Bangladesh is
living illegally in India abinav says
why is the BJP not doing anything about
the rohinga issue the I don't know how
many ringas we have in India probably
lacks what what's the point of having A1
10 trillion dollar economy
infrastructure Etc when our next next
generation will not get benefits because
of the the infiltrators who have been
settled in India the illegal immigration
is increasing and so on these are very
valid points that are being made over
here and this is something that uh we
need to
uh hold the government accountable
to look is it is it wrong for the people
to to expect the government to deport
the millions of illegal immigrants that
we know are living in India every
everyone knows this you go to any major
city you will find very visible evidence
of incredible numbers of illegal
Bangladesh's and rohingyas we know where
the ringas have been settled they've
been settled in Jammu they've been
settled in various other parts of India
imagine them being settled all the way
in
Jammu why is India harboring these
illegal infiltrators why what do we get
from it as a nation it's a burden on our
tax payer it's a it's a burden on the
Indian economy in
2014 the government of India had stated
that there are roughly 5 CR which is 50
million illegal Bangladesh is living in
India that's in 2014 today is 2024 end
of
2024 what's the number today has it
doubled it's at least the same right if
and most likely a whole lot more must
have come in through the poorest borders
so maybe we have a 100 m million
Bangladesh's and ringas living in India
can you imagine the burden on the Indian
taxpayer the burden in the on the Indian
economy on the Indian infrastructure and
they will multiply and they will get all
the Adar cards and all all the documents
they'll become
Indians and it's don't you think it's a
gigantic problem for
India why do we Harbor these
people
and look the prime min had had promised
in 2014 when he was the Prime
ministerial candidate that he will
Deport the bangladeshis the question is
what happened sh would you like to see
evidence of that let me put evidence of
that since we talking about this why
not let me put this video on the
screen check it out this is a video from
10 years ago April 28 2014 okay it's
from times now let's let's briefly play
it bjp's Prime ministri nomin now has
issued a stun warning to Illegal
Bangladeshi immigrants now while
addressing a rally in Bengal Narendra
Modi says that he will send them packing
if the NDA forms the government at the
center another so yeah I'll I'll stop it
there I'll not play the entire video the
point is that Mr Modi had promised in
2014 that if he was elected and became
prime minister after that so and so date
of of May or whatever date he mentioned
the Bangladesh is will be
deported so what happened
sir how many Bangladesh's have been
deported since since May 2014 and how
many have come in is it wrong to to to
hold the government accountable to its
promises nothing has been done
clearly you will see Bangladeshi
infiltrators all over the major cities
of India IND all over the place they
take over entire economic
sectors they monopolize entire economic
sectors and and why are they being
welcomed in
India because they they constitute very
important vote Banks without which
politicians can't get
elected so they are settled in ghettos
in various in various cities in India
slums and every locality every Municipal
Ward or whatever has Bang slum or some
kind of Slum and those people are
allowed to settle there they're
regularized and the condition is that
you'll keep voting for us and that's how
allegedly and that's why allegedly
Bangladesh is are so welcome in
India it's it's a huge problem it it
points to the incredible humongous
amount of corruption we have in India
and this is a national security threat
it is a civilizational threat for
India and why has no action been taken
the past 10
years despite promises being made
so yeah it's these are valid questions
and people need to ask these questions
because otherwise what's the point of
having A1 trillion economy 20 trillion
economy becoming a visha guru becoming a
superpower what superpower what Vish
Guru when you are compromis from within
a 100 million I mean it's it's larger
than the population of most
Nations and they are not pro-india they
are they are in no way aligned with
India's cultural or civilizational
values they are in no way aligned with
India's national interests and we are
harboring them on our territory on our
soil on our
soil I just don't get what's happening I
just don't get it I don't know what the
government is doing what the leadership
is doing what have they' been doing for
the past 10 years are they so helpless
that they can't take any action then why
are you what's the point of growing the
economy then if you are building the
economy and creating infrastructure for
these people and their
descendants I don't get
it okay vikam Ador says has West Asia
almost slipped out of the Russian sphere
of influence with the Assad regime being
toppled now Putin is thinking of
Shifting his Naval base from Tartus in
Syria to somewhere else in Libya and now
Iran is the only the sole remaining Ally
of Russia that still exists in the
region once again let's go to the map
what's happened we know we know what's
happened so we will not go and discuss
what has happened we know that Assad has
been overthrown and so on but what's the
consequences of this let that's what we
to look at so once again we go to the
West Asia
region um and north of that we have
Russia of course we have we know where
Moscow is and then we have the Caucasus
region which is between the Black Sea
and the Caspian Sea and South of the
Caucasus we have the region that we are
discussing West Asia so the major
players are turkey and Iran and of
course the super major player is the US
and it's greatest Ally Israel and the US
has a number of other allies in the
region which Saudi Arabia uh and so
on so so Assad has fallen which means
that essentially
turkey and Israel have conquered Syria
and now they will cooperate on the on
what happens next in Syria and the
long-term evolution of the leadership
and governance in Syria the same way
what we saw what happened in Iraq post
2023 at the aler of Saddam Hussein Syria
is no longer a a geopolitical force in
the region it it is now it it now has
the same status that Iraq has which is a
nation that has no leadership and no
hard power anymore and because of this
Iran has lost access to
Lebanon and Iran is kind of
isolated so it's a victory for turkey
and for Israel and it's a defeat for
Iran and for Russia and when it comes to
Russia they have the Latakia base and
the Tartus base military bases there
they have one Naval base and and
at least one Air Force Base and most
likely they will have to vacate these
bases so it looks like some kind of
agreement was reached with Russia also
especially between turkey and Russia
that turkey will kind of
uh give up Libya to Russia and they will
take over Syria Syria is rich in oil and
gas and all that and turkey and Israel
will benefit from that and Russia has to
now vacate Syria and maybe they will
take over parts of Libya that seems to
be the kind of deal that has happened
behind the scenes and in the in in the
coming days weeks and months we will see
uh the details slowly but surely come to
light in in the form of actual uh facts
on the ground so it is definitely a
setback for Russia it is a significant
setback for Iran as well I think Iran is
now going to be in a an increasingly
more precarious situation in 2025 it is
possible that by the middle of 25 or by
the end of 25 Iran could find itself at
War that's also a possibility I hope War
doesn't happen war is not good for the
for anyone but yeah it's good
geopolitically for various Powers it's
bad for the common people it's terrible
it's it's it's tragic but geopolitically
all change happens through implicit or
explicit Warf
so yes Russia has suffered a setback
Iran has suffered a significant
setback and one hopes that Iran is not
not not next after what happened to Iraq
and then Syria one hope so because uh
that will significantly change the
balance of power and Dynamics in the
region and we in India we don't have any
issues with Iran and it's good for us if
Iran continues to exist as a significant
power in the region so then they have it
it's a set setback for Russia and for
Iran and it's possible that sometime in
25 Iran could find itself at war
with with a
coalition that could be leaded could be
headed by the US and Israel it's
possible it's possible one hope it
doesn't happen happen but it's
possible okay let's take some questions
from the live chat let's do that as well
okay Tanish chaan says us says it that
Pakistan cannot continue the missile
program so apparently news has emerged
that Pakistan is is pursuing a ballistic
missile program an ICBM program
intercontinental ballistic missile
program with missiles that could
eventually end up having the US within
their range that's the kind of news that
seems to have come out and the Americans
have imposed sanctions on some
Pakistani entities
apparently well we have to understand
that Pakistan is a us vasal Pakistan is
a US proxy so whatever happens in
Pakistan happens with us consent and if
the pakistanis are developing longer
range missiles they only objective would
be India why would they want to Target
the
US the only objective would be to be
able to strike wherever they want within
India because India is such a large
territory uh so look I I don't know
what's the point of this
whole this
whole what's happening right now drama
let's say uh but I don't see the
Pakistan is being a threat for the US
ever maybe it's just to uh convince the
world that Pakistan is a Sovereign
Nation and it has its own agenda maybe
that's the only thing I don't see
anything else you know being behind
this geopolitical du says will we be
able ever able to explore the ocean
depth yeah the ocean is more mysterious
than outer space and uh exploring the
ocean entails lots of challenges because
the deeper you go in the ocean the the
more alien the Environ environment
becomes once you go below a depth of
roughly 100 beors there's complete
darkness there no light can reach can go
further down so it's complete darkness
pitch dark in the ocean and uh as you go
deeper under the ocean the water
pressure also increases significantly
and that's also a huge challenge the the
temperature also drops a lot so it's
very cold very dark and and extremely
high
pressure and because of that it's very
difficult for humans to explore these
parts of the ocean especially the deeper
parts of the ocean it's easier to
explore space than to do that but with
with the Advent of new technologies like
autonomous underwater Vehicles
autonomous submarines Marine drones and
so on we may be able to eventually map
the entire entirety of the ocean floor
in the coming years uh but for humans to
go all the way down there several
kilometers down it's it's extremely
difficult because uh the technology does
exist the deepest point under the ocean
is called the Mariana Trench which is
off the coast of the Philippines and
humans have descended all the way down
there I think it's it's below it's it's
deeper than 10 or 11 kilometers very
deep but humans have indeed gone all the
way down there but the technology is
very expensive and so it's not something
that everybody can do very few people
can do that uh but yeah eventually I
suppose we will be able to explore all
of it maybe in the next 100 years or so
with the Advent of new
technologies okay uh let's see one or
two more live chat questions
um uh
prasa gutam says can India have freedom
of speech like the us in the
future uh does the US have complete
freedom of speech I don't think so there
are so many things you can't say in the
US I mean before Elon Musk took over
Twitter Twitter was under the
administration and ownership of Jack
dorsy wasn't it and they were they were
Shadow
Banning so many people they were
permanently Banning people they
permanently banned the sitting president
of the United States before the next
president took office right they banned
Donald Trump you call that freedom of
speech there's so much you can't say in
the US you'll be cancelled so
technically it may not be illegal but if
you say it then you will have real world
consequences very rapid and very harsh
consequences you'll be cancelled uh if
you are a famous person and you say
certain things you will lose all your
brand brand deals all the contracts
you'll become penalized very quickly so
there's no freedom of speech
in the US you can say things that are
socially acceptable or acceptable uh in
the current scheme of them things but
you can't say things that are not
acceptable in the current scheme of
things uh so I don't see the us as a
nation that has freedom of speech and
even if you technically may have that uh
there's no freedom of consequences from
speech and when it comes to India also
so there is no Society where you have
complete absolutely Universal freedom of
speech and even if you may technically
have that on paper you cannot say things
and expect there to be no consequences
for what you have
said so that sort of idealistic utopian
world doesn't exist there are always
consequences for your actions and for
your speech and so the US has a whole
bunch of things that you can't say and a
whole categories of things you cannot
say
in India there's a whole different
category of things you can't say India
is a socialist secular Nation there are
certain individuals you cannot criticize
if you criticize certain individuals who
are not naming by the way then you go to
jail and you'll be oppressed and and and
all kinds of terrible things will happen
to you and that sort of thing and there
are
certain other things you cannot explore
certain things you can't say and so
that's just how it is but go to go to
other countries go to Canada for example
you can't say a
thing
uh there are lots of things you can't
say in Canada also right the the
Canadian government has its own Super
fascist approach to things uh Mr Trudeau
will talk about freedom of speech and
democracy and blah blah blah in India
but when it comes to the same kind of
protest in Canada he will crack down
them crack down upon them brutally so
there's no real such Freedom anywhere in
the world even in the so-called liberal
West so yeah I don't think it's ever
possible and do we really want uh
absolute freedom of speech do you want
people to have the right to say
absolutely
anything I mean there are things that
are actually criminal
right I mean there are a whole bunch of
categories of actions that are
classified as
crimes and some crimes are really
heinous crimes
do you want people have to have the
freedom to say that these crimes are
fine and
to promote or or Justify or glorify such
crimes you know it doesn't work like
that so there can never be any absolute
complete freedom of speech anywhere in
the world and the US certainly is not
that sort of nation where you have
genuine freedom of speech and neither is
India that that's just the way it is
okay let's go back to uh questions that
people and and things that people have
said in the
comments okay I usually never take very
long long multiple paragraph questions
or statements but for once I am doing
that so this is by Ali Raza Rai who is
from Iran so this is a person
perspective on on things so let's see
what he has to say an Iranian guy here
and I want to share my thoughts with you
about my about my Indian cousins firstly
Mr chaa you said something that you
should remember number forever Ira
Israel is no one's Ally let let alone a
vasal they may have some vasal and he
says that the biggest one is the us but
they surely aren't anybody's wasal so
okay that's the first statement he makes
I agree that they are no one's M wasal I
don't think they are the u United States
is wasal I don't think so I don't think
the US owns and controls the nation of
Israel and he says it's it's the other
around that Israel
actually is the nation that controls the
US that has the us as as it's wasal well
let me not go into that at all but
that's what he is saying okay I'm not
going to comment on that next I am
shocked secondly by the fact that most
Indians consider Israel to be their Ally
because Israel shares no
values with the people of India the
biggest one in India is cultural
tolerance which Israel is empty off
that's what he says so I would agree
that India and Israel are culturally
very different we don't have any shared
culture or shared values or civilization
civilization values we are very
different cultures India is a dharmic
culture with a 10,000 plus year old
history Israel is the original abrahamic
culture which with with a history that
goes back about 3,000 years and their
value system and their culture is
extremely different
from the dharmic value system I'm not
saying this is right or that is wrong
it's just very different the two
cultures are kind of di diam
diametrically opposite of each other in
a lot lot of ways that's something
Indians don't seem to realize next so
please understand that uh by by putting
this out there I am not being
anti-israel or pro-israel or anything I
have absolutely nothing against Israel I
admire the nation of Israel in a lot of
ways but let's understand the various
perspectives that people have and let's
understand what the Indian perspective
should
be so next Israel is the number one Ally
of aeran which is a fact yes it's a fact
also Israel has a great relationship
with
turkey and both these nations are sword
enemies of India turkey and aeran of
course and of course India is is
supporting the nation of Armenia
with which we have two and a half
thousands or 3,000 year of years of
relationship very good relations and the
Turks and the aeran is want to wipe
Armenia off of the map of the world and
India is trying to ensure that Armenia
is not wiped out and who is who is the
Ally of aeran and turkey in this matter
it's Israel Israel is opposing India's
actions in this particular matter when
it comes to Armenia aeran
right and uh erdogan and Netanyahu are
completely collaborating in destroying
the Syrian government and taking Syria
yes and Syria had a reasonably good
relation with relationship with India
India and Mr Assad we had a reasonably
good relationship Assad was never
anti-india Syria was never
anti-india right and do you forget
Israel taking all its gas and oil from
turkey and aeran will that's also a fact
no no questions about it and yeah this
is something I've spoken about multiple
times including on debates on Republic
TV I've said this about the Israel and
Pakistan relationship I must say there
is plenty of evidence that proves Israel
is helping terrorists in Southwest
Pakistan against Iran so I don't think
Israeli agents can in infiltrate
Pakistani land without the pakistanis
knowing it interesting point that Mr Rai
raises over here I have spoken about
this in the past that what's the nature
of the Israel Pakistan
relationship I mean Pakistan is a US
wasal the US is Israel's biggest
Ally so what's the Israel Pakistan
relationship right and there is no
satisfactory answer to that Israel and
Pakistan don't
have I mean the pakistanis say that they
don't recognize Israel blah blah blah
all words all words but on the ground
what's happening right yeah there you
have it and for the sake of God please
engrave what Mr chavada said about the
flag on a golden slab and place it on
top of a billboard for everyone to see
the only flag that you should ever place
anywhere be it on your home door or
social media or anywhere else is your
own flag not somebody else's flag
Indians love putting up other nations
flags on their social media profiles why
the only flag on your profile should be
your own so I completely agree with Mr
Rai over here and uh and lastly if you
see Mr Nathan Yahoo shows so much
audacity
in his actions it's because he's not
play paying the bills from his own
pocket he's paying the bills from the US
taxpayers pockets okay and Israel is
nothing without the US it's Bal
according to Mr Rai if you see they are
doing all of these things it's because
they know that they have the US with all
of its might behind them which is true
Israel is able to do whatever it does
because of the unconditional support it
always receives from the United
States so it's very interesting to see
the Persian perspective on this matter
and it it is very much and very largely
in line with what I have been saying
that look from my perspective I have
nothing against
Israel but we have to understand that
the India Israel relationship is based
on
shared on limited shared interests and
not ba broad shared values or shared
culture or shared
civilization India is a huge Nation with
the largest economy outside of the West
which which is why India is attractive
for Israel so we have shared interests
in a variety of
things and which is why that's why we
are cooperating but to imagine that
Israel is is look there are no friends
in geopolitics to imagine that Israel is
India's friend I'm not saying India
Israel is India Enemy by any metric
whatsoever but to imagine that India
Israel is India's friend is going a
little bit too far my main point is that
I have nothing against Israel but we
have to be
realistic in in viewing the India Israel
relationship it's not some ancient
relationship based in shared ethnicity
and shared culture and trade values it
is more of a
relationship that is based on Mutual
benefit and and and mutual
interests interests not values interests
not
culture there you have
it okay prai Paul says there have been
reports of former US military officials
and individuals of similar rank openly
giving training to cookie terrorists in
Manipur with cookie terrorists surfacing
prominently X okay that the video has
come out on X Videos have come out on X
now despite this if the government of
India fails to take decisive action
doesn't it raise questions about their
credibility even if they may be working
on plans behind the c curtain to address
the situation how do you view this
ongoing development and its impact on
India's internal security
stance right so let let's let's find the
news report I mean there's so many news
reports let's find one of this and put
it on the screen from from Twitter or
X so this is a tweet from December 21st
from yesterday from India today which
says that American evangelist Daniel
Courtney faces a backlash after a
perpared video shows him Distributing
drones and bulletproof jackets to the
kooki terrorist in Manipur this sparked
concerns about his over his
controversial activities and accusations
of stoking communal tensions in India
and so on so forth and these are just uh
images of the guy who has been a US
Marine who has once again Israel
connections right the the the Israel
angle again
surfaces and
uh and then his activities in India in
Telangana in Manipur in in
isol which is uh
mizoram and uh he seems to be a believer
of Christ with ties to is is and and so
on and this India Today tweet says that
this American fellow Daniel kurtney is
facing a black
backlash So Daniel curtney according to
India Today is facing a backlash my
point is why is Daniel curtney
an agent of the
US facing a
backlash the bigger question
is why is he being allowed to open at
with impunity in Telangana in Manipur in
mizoram in isol distributing Bibles and
distributing bulletproof uniforms and
distributing drones and giving speeches
and traveling all over the place why is
he being allowed to do this should
should Daniel kurtney be facing the
backlash or should the government of
India be facing a
backlash isn't it the job of the
government of India the duty and the
responsibility of the government of
India not to allow such activ ities to
happen on Indian Territory or are we not
a sovereign nation has the government of
India abdicated its responsibility
towards the national
security so what prai Paul is asking and
what so many people are asking is it
raises questions about the credibility
of the government of
India you may perhaps be working on some
great plans behind the curtains but on
the ground all of this is happening and
you're doing nothing to stop it
it it makes it look like we are no
longer a Sovereign Nation and the US has
been given free reign to create cooki
land for Christ out of Manipur mizoram
and Burma and Bangladesh looks like
that's what's happening I mean from what
we see happening on the ground right it
looks like
that so my question is very simple why
has the government of India not taken
cognizance of what this individual was
doing and how many other individuals
must be doing we don't know right we
just know of one such instance from
social media about this guy called
Daniel kurtney a former US Marine but
there are we know that there are so many
more such
people who abuse the tourist visa of
India to indulge in such activities they
come to India on tourist visas and a
whole bunch of them will go and in and
engage in evangelization activities
Christian conversion activities
some of them will go to sensitive parts
of India I don't know how they get
access to these to these areas and and
do things like what this guy Daniel
Courtney is doing so my question is what
is the government of India doing are you
people completely clueless are you
people completely
incompetent have you given up I don't
get
it this guy has been in India for such a
long time it looks like he's been making
multiple visits to
India and he's getting drones he's
getting bullet proof jackets
where are what are his
sources where is he getting this
military grade equipment
from I just don't know what's happening
really H anyway so what PR Paul asks is
completely legitimate very valid
questions and I don't have the answers
to these questions the government of
India needs to answer at some point in
time they have to answer to the people
of India what they have been
doing
yeah okay ultimate power A1 says
ultimately does the US spread
Christianity to spread its influence or
does the US spread it it its influence
to spread Christianity or
both look understand this thing there
are three abrahamic religions okay these
abrahamic
religions are political
religions the objective of these
religions is
ultimately control and power
or people and or territories that's the
actual objective I have personally
nothing against any religion look if if
so and so person wants to convert to so
and so religion let them do it right
it's a personal choice but when
conversion activities are being done
with the objective of demographic
re-engineering and it's happening on an
industrial Mass scale that's a national
security threat so I have nothing
against any specific religion but when
you're using religion as a geopolitical
tool as a social re-engineering tool as
a demographic re re-engineering tool
that's a national security threat and
that's what I have an objection to and
the government of India should also have
an objection to that so Christianity is
a tool that that the foreign powers use
not just in India but across Asia
they've used that in Burma they've
converted very large numbers of Burmese
people to Christianity they've done the
same thing in Cambodia in Vietnam the
the mountain people the Hill People the
remote tribes they are the ones who are
the most vulnerable to these predators
and they are all converted to
Christianity and the Japanese and the
Chinese noted this centuries ago that
when their citizens when their people
convert to
Christianity they somehow I don't know
how but they somehow spontaneously
develop extr territorial loyalties and
anti-national tendencies and that's why
Japan and China both historically have
cracked down on Christian ity so it's
not about the religion it's about the
use of the religion for geopolitical
purposes and for the purpose of meddling
in the internal affairs of a nation and
the for the purpose of demographic
re-engineering on massive
scales so the re the religion is used to
spread geopolitical influence it's not
done the other way around the US doesn't
doesn't spread its influence to
propagate Christianity it propagates
Christianity to spread its influence and
to expand the area which is under its
influence next Vikram Ador says how
significant do you think India's
relationship with the African continent
is and what could be the next big step
for India to expand its influence there
considering China and Russia are making
significant inroads in Africa
okay
so Africa is the largest continent it's
huge gigantic we don't realize that when
we look at the mercant meraner
projection map but it's the it's it's a
huge continent and the population of
Africa all the nations put together is
slightly less than the population of
India so that's an interesting uh
factual tidbit now
um Africa has historically been
colonized by the Europeans and
completely devastated and ravaged and
today the major religions in Africa are
the two abrahamic religions Christianity
and Islam and before the Europeans it
was colonized by the Arabs okay tragic
history in the past thousand plus years
in Africa um and now we have this
artificially created Nations if we look
at the map of Africa let's go to the map
once again if you look at the map of
Africa we we will see straight lines
everywhere straight lines which are
lines drawn on a map not organic
boundaries or borders but artificial
borders between artificial Nations and
because of that you have all kinds of
civil wars and lots of conflicts and
strife all across Africa all the time
the democra the Democratic Republic of
Congo
DRC is a gigantic nation that is
essentially
ungoverned um no real government
whatever government exists is being
remote controlled from outside from
Rwanda and uh it's the nation is being
exploited for resources and you will see
similar situations everywhere else
across Africa the sahil region is
notoriously C prone and so
now the French have kind of lost a lot
of their influence in Africa in the past
few years because of very poor
policies uh the Russians have made some
inroads in Africa through the Wagner
group and the Chinese have been trying
to uh
establish strongholds in Africa for the
past 20 plus years by by doing these
projects you know infrastructure
building projects and so on but they
have not been actually very successful
to the extent that we think they
have now many of these African nations
they would love to have India as a
benefactor or let's say a big brother a
nation that has no interest in
plundering pillaging and ravaging them
in a nation who is willing to help in a
nation who yeah essentially a nation
that's willing to help in a mutually
beneficial way African lots of African
nations would love to have this so there
I think there's a huge opportunity for
India and Africa uh lots of African
nations regard the Western Powers as
Predators very rightfully so uh they may
also have big question marks about what
Russia's objectives are in Africa and uh
China hasn't particularly succeeded
China also has had
policies that have not really worked in
Africa of course they have built all
this infrastructure and so on so forth
but it has not really benefited them too
much so
Africa is a huge opportunity for India
to expand its sphere of influence not
power but sphere of influence but when
it comes to Indian foreign policy
establishment we are blind to Africa we
are a nation that's that we seem to be
driven by status so we want to have
relations with Nations that are the
Elite Nations the G8 Nations G7 Nations
the top 10 economies in the world the
Western Nations the powerful Nations and
we completely ignore and disregard
Africa once in a while we will have an
India Africa Summit or something but
these are
all essentially cosmetic uh
policies that we are doing once in a
while it's just like raising slogans and
all that but we are not really investing
in the relationship with with the
African nations why don't we have
embassies and consulates all across
Africa why don't we have 5,000 diplomats
dedicated only to Africa we don't even
have 5,000 diplomats in total we have
less than 2,000 diplomats in total one
of the smallest diplomatic U forces in
the world
we have less diplomats than Singapore
has we don't have any Africa experts in
Academia where is the Indian um academic
Department dedicated to the the nation
of let's say Angola or let's say Burkina
Faso or Ghana do we have any experts on
Ghana or Benin or let's say Sagal we
don't have any of that Togo is a very
interesting and important Nation we
don't have any experts on that so we
simply disregard Africa because it's
poor it's a huge opportunity for India
and you know how we can benefit from
this whenever we have a a vote in the
United Nations if we have good relations
with these African nations they will all
vote for us they may be poor they may be
impoverished they may not be powerful
they may be broken down but they all
have one
vote so why don't we leverage
that uh so I think Africa represents a
huge opportunity for India not just
diplomatically not just from a People to
People perspective uh in so many
different ways there Africa is full of
resources if you have good relations
with various Nations we can get those
resources in a mutually beneficial way
and and so on so much can be done
there's so much
potential in the India Africa
relationship and Africa is so large with
so many nations and so many people that
we need
to invest more in our relationship with
Africa thus far I our foreign policy our
foreign establishment has completely
turned a blind eye to Africa I think it
is not a wise thing I think we need to
change the way we approach Africa so I
think there's tremendous
potential in India's relationship with
the African
continent so what's the next big step
for us I think we should encourage uh
various universities to set up
departments
that specialize in Africa whether it's
historical research whether it's
sociological
research or political science research
in Africa we need to do that that's
that's one thing secondly we need to set
up embassies and consulates all across
Africa in every single African nation no
matter how big or small or rich or poor
we need to have that and we need to
cultivate the relationship with each of
these nations that's what we need to do
we are a nation that is not hegemonic we
are not there to plunder these nations
they they understand that so they will
welcome such steps from for from
India but I think the first step we have
to do we to take is to
expand our foreign Ministry the number
of diplomats who work for the foreign
ministry right now we have less than
2,000 I think a nation of India's heft
and India's standing should have at
least 5 10,000 diplomats specializing in
various Nations that's what we need to
do
right okay adash Naran rout says you
told us the hard power of a country
brings its soft power influence to other
countries then how about K-pop Japanese
anime Korean films Etc they are very
famous around the world which brings a
positive response from the people about
these countries right so yes a soft
power that's that's an important debate
we definitely need to have soft power
hard power all that so hard power is
economic power plus military power plus
power projection capabilities plus
nuclear weapons and so on so forth all
that is hard power it's the it's the
hard power the scary power economic plus
military power mainly soft power so what
is soft power so for Any Nation soft
power is the capacity of that Nation to
persuade others to
do what that Nation wants so what is
India soft power India soft power is the
capacity that India has to persuade
others to do what India
wants how much soft power does India
have is is a different matter So Soft
power is persuasion power soft power
rests on the ability of my nation to
shape the
preferences of others without the use of
force or or coercion or violence
persuasion not for forcing somebody not
arm twisting someone you pursuade them
so you do this through intangible
assets an attractive personality an
attractive culture an attractive brand
nations are Brands so if your brand is
attractive that's your soft power so all
of that then your political values your
political ideology your culture your
civilizational values your
Institutions and your policies
which are seen as legitimate and having
moral Authority so all of that is soft
power and
and
legitimacy and moral Authority is
Central to soft power okay so you can
have an
attractive
brand but if you lack legitimacy and
moral Authority then you have no soft
power
okay um so when a nation is able to
sincerely attract and convince other
nations using its values and set set of
practices then your nation is considered
to be to have an effective soft power
now let's take the
example of
K-pop what is what is South Korea's
image South Korea's image is predicated
largely on K-POP and skincare routines
and Instagram influences and all that
it's it's good branding sure it's
attractive brand in but does it give
Korea moral
Authority does it give Korea
legitimacy it doesn't
right having an attractive glossy
glamorous image is not
enough you also need to be seen as
having moral Authority and having
legitimacy legitimacy and moral
legitimacy right when it comes to codian
films and all that so that's just half
of the job done you also need to be the
the you need to also have the other half
so when India if you look at
India India's culture India's
civilizational values give it a
tremendous amount of moral Authority and
moral legitimacy but India's brand isn't
great India doesn't have the kind of
K-pop and the Glamorous thing India
actually has a rather poor image
internationally
right as a nation with poor
infrastructure and and uh poor
experience for visitors and all of that
there are lots of bad things that are
said about India so India's overall
image isn't great but India's culture
gives it moral Authority and legitimacy
of course
India's if you look at the Modern
secular socialist state of India then
the policies we follow are not grounded
in Indian culture anymore but still
Indian culture is so old and ancient
that it gives us a certain amount of
legitimacy and moral Authority
so so that's the difference between uh
the the brand value of Korea and India
or or Japanese en Enemy versus India
Japan is a different matter Korea is a
different matter but
overall what I have said is that your
soft
power is useless unless you have hard
power the more hard power you have the
more your soft power can become
efficacious and useful the soft power is
pointless without having hard power
because at the end of the day you want
to get things done right so it's it's a
pretty complicated topic but overall
that's how it is so soft power is is is
all about legitimacy and moral Authority
and also the brand image and all that
but at the end of the day if you have
great soft power but you are not a
Sovereign
Nation then what's the point of that
soft power what's the point of it
South Korea is under permanent US
military occupation so is Japan neither
nation is Sovereign both nations are
under permanent fullscale foreign
occupation then what's the point of
having soft
power there's no point because you're
not sovereign you're not an independent
nation the same can be said about
Europe Europe is not a sovereign entity
the European Union none of the European
Union Nations is a sovereign entity they
don't have any control over their
currency they don't have any control
over their borders they don't have any
control over the laws they can pass or
or or or repeal they don't have any
control over the policies they don't
have any control in in the case of NATO
Nations they don't have any control of
their own militaries what's where's the
sovereignty so you may have a great
image and a great brand but you have no
sovereignty then your soft power is zero
essentially despite seemingly being
great so it's a complicated topic but
you going to understand how it really
works okay balam Putin says what can we
learn from the modern state of China and
what's your thoughts on their criticism
about the colonial mindset of
India so the Chinese have criticized
India a lot what do they criticize India
for one of the criticisms the Chinese
have leveled at India is that India is
an example of of too much
democracy India has is a genuine
democracy elections every other week
somewhere or the other M Municipal level
District level uh state level Central
level whatever so many elections all
over the place all the
time so many laws but nothing happens
nothing works you have laws for
everything but nothing is implemented
you have corruption everywhere you have
got a broken down infrastructure you
have pollution you have corruption you
have garbage all over the
place and so
on extremely inefficient nation very
corrupt system system that doesn't serve
the nation the system that doesn't serve
the people and yet a great democracy
right the world's largest democracy so
that's one criticism the Chinese have
always leveled at India India is the
best example of why democracy doesn't
work that's one criticism that they've
leveled at India
consistently um the second
criticism is not something they say
directly but you can see that they have
a certain amount of contempt towards
India why what is the source of the
contempt they see India as a western sto
as a colonized Nation a nation that had
the opportunity to throw away the
baggage of colonialism but we have
chosen to continue
that and that's why they have a lot of
contempt for India is there contempt
Justified I think it
is we have colonized ourselves even
further since
1947 in 1947 most Indians did not have
English English education most
newspapers or whatever were not in
English today we are completely
deracinated completely westernized we've
lost our culture we no longer use our
languages the entire education system is
in English you you can't get a good job
if you don't speak in English and if you
don't give the interview in English the
entire Judicial System higher judicial
system is can only speak in English the
entire government the the the the
Constitution is a western copy pasted
Constitution all of our laws are Western
copy pasted laws our institutions are
Colonial institutions what's original
about us it's just everything is an
inferior copy of something the West has
done we have no self-respect
we just want to ape the West we want to
ape today what the West did 50 years
ago so that's why the Chinese have a
large significant amount of contempt for
India and I think that contempt is
Justified and their their criticism of
India's democracy is also Justified
because nothing gets done in
India so what can we learn from the
China from from from the Modern Nation
of
China look China gets things done
China prioritizes its National interest
China doesn't let all doesn't allow
others to interfere in its internal
matters we allow everybody to interfere
in our internal matters we have a whole
new artificial Nation project being
being operated upon in our Far East
kiland for Christ you think China will
tolerate such such a project by the
Americans you think China will tolerate
the Americans doing a cou a coup in
their neighborhood like what what
happened with Pakistan with Bangladesh
in the recent two three years with India
in the subcontinent there's so much we
can learn from
China China has done many mistakes made
many mistakes in the past during
especially during the time of maong
maong the great Le Leap Forward the
cultural revolution huge mistakes were
made but those were rectified especially
after they shoing him to
power so China overall the Chinese
Communist Party serves the nation serves
the people of course there is corruption
at various levels and all every nation
has that the most corrupt nation in the
world is the
us but in China the corruption
um it doesn't really affect the people
the way it affects people in
India and so on so there is so much
India can learn from China the Chinese
efficiency the Chinese U ambition the
gen they they have a purpose India
doesn't have a purpose right what is
India's Mission what is India's Mission
as a nation
China has a mission as a
nation China China's mission is to
replace and displace the us as the
world's largest economy and most
powerful
Nation they have very clear purpose
every sector industrial sector every
academic sector has a very clear
long-term vision and purpose we as a
nation India are
clueless aimless purposeless what is the
national purpose of India
Today do we have an objective or is our
objective just to keep existing and keep
arguing and squabbling and voting every
every few
weeks what's the national purpose of
India what is our national
motto yeah sat there but in the in India
the opposite actually happens it's
always untruth that wins in
India so there is so much we can learn
from Nations who are doing better than
us the Chinese have
there's a lot to admire when it comes to
China a lot to admire so there's a lot
we can learn from
them ultimate power A1 says did the
Chinese Two Face similar racism and
criticism when they were in the initial
phase of growth just like India of
course they did so today India's India's
per capita GDP is about $2,500 and
today's dollar money yes in today's US
dollar uh exchange rates when China
had a GDP of about the same what we have
today in India they also went through
the whole process the same process that
we are going
through they have also they also face
racism from the West they are also made
fun they were also made fun of by the
West the West used to make fun of China
a
lot they used to be Little
China and so on but the Chinese just
carried for carried on growing They
carried on working as hard as they Poss
POS could and the inflection point the
turning point for China was the 2008
Olympics in which they demonstrated that
they could
do what they could do the Olympics
better than what the West could do they
were able to demonstrate they were a
force to be reckoned with a nation with
ex extremely high
standards the Olympic opening ceremony
was essentially an exercise in shock and
awe it really stunned the
West that's how well it was it was done
in India when we have something like the
Commonwealth Games or something if you
see the opening ceremony it's you it
want you want to cringe if you look at
the 26th January March past in
Delhi you can see it's done by
amateurs it's done by people who don't
really care it's so shy it's so shabby
when the Chinese did the 2008 Olympic
Games opening and closing C it was an
exercise in shock and awe it suddenly
for the first
time the the the awareness dawned on the
west that China is here to compete they
are a nation that means business and
they are capable of extremely high
standards so they did that now what are
we doing are we going to have an
inflection point somewhere a turning
point somewhere do we really have high
standards in
India that's what we have to ask
ourselves so right now we are we are in
a rather initial stage compared to where
China is
today vun Kalia says I'm 31 years old I
wanted to learn coding because earlier
whatever I indulged in did not pan out
well so can I go into the coding field
as a fresher at this age and I'm also
having doubts about AIS because people
said that AI will cut will will eat into
the jobs for coders in the
future I think it's not a good idea
anymore to learn
coding and and and go into that
field because today AI can do anything a
programmer can do much faster much more
efficiently and much
better and the latest
updates in the AI
systems have been kind of transformative
and and they game changers I don't think
there's any future for for coders
anymore a person with zero experience of
coding will be able to get things done
just by telling AI what he or she
wants and uh having having an a
subscription to whatever AI system it's
it's like having 20 programmers working
for you I don't think it's a good idea
to at the at whatever age to get into
coding and hope that that will give you
a longterm F long long-term career not
going to
happen yeah so here is one field where
we can see AI destroy an entire
field AI will do all the coding now you
don't need programmers you can just tell
AI to do it it'll do
it okay aunia P says as IIT students
what should be our priority our own
career or our country most people like
to go abroad because of the
opportunities available outside I am in
a dilemma about whether to put myself
first or my
country look my advice will never change
it is consistently the same always
prioritize yourself
first when you
are in the beginning of your career
let's say at the age of 20 21
whatever you have to prioritize as your
career you have to put yourself
first if you want to serve your country
you can't do it by having a broken
career or or or or a career that's not
doing
well so if you are getting opportunities
to go abroad to advance your career
please do that put yourself first put
your career first and go wherever it
takes
you get all the skills all the
experience that you can become as
wealthy as possible and in 20
years if you want you can return to
India and then you can make a real
impact when you are completely
inexperienced when you haven't even
started your career you are jobless you
are broke you are poor penniless what
will you be able to do to help the
country only people only the only people
who can genuinely help the country is
persons of substance
it's people who have experience people
who have Knowledge and Skills and people
who have the wealth that's needed to
make an
impact so please put yourself first put
your own career
first first become a person of genuine
substance and then serve your country
that's the order of things that you
should follow
har Krishna says I am in the third year
of college I have never had any true
friends I'm currently residing in the US
with my parents I commute multiple hours
every day to go to college and come back
I'm very lonely I regret my entire life
I literally have no one to talk to
sometimes there are months since I talk
to someone I really wanted to experience
hostile life but my parents did not let
me to let me go there they have ample
money but they didn't let me go there
now I will never be able to experience
this time again and we'll always regret
this what to do I am extremely depressed
sometimes I want to run away or Escape
these circumstances during my school
life which was in India even that was
very
bad right okay it looks like so your
parents clearly are have enough
money so it looks like from what you
have said that your parents seem to be
the
problem so look I'm sure they mean well
but maybe their their policies have
turned out to be uh counterproductive
perhaps not everybody is blessed with
great parents sometimes par parents can
themselves be a problem sometimes it's
unfortunate but it
happens uh now you you said that you go
to college right so what you need to do
is if you go to college you will have
classmates there who will be studying in
the same Department same courses who who
be taking the same courses as you make
friends there talk to them create
relationships
there um it's it's I'm I'm you've not
said it but I'm assuming that your
parents are paying for your college
education which means that you have a
financial dependency on your parents
which every kid every every young person
has until they start earning for
themselves um and you are travel you're
commuting multiple hours every day which
means that you are living in one
location and your college is in a very
different location significantly further
away so either you can convince your
convince your parents to uh to give you
the funds to so that you can live in a
dorm or or an apartment or something
near your college because of which so
the effect that will have is that you
won't have to commute multiple hours
every day but if your parents aren't
willing to do that then you may have to
wait one more year until you finish your
college and then get a job and then
you'll be able to have your own social C
cir and life at the end of the day the
make the thing that makes or breaks
everything is is financial stability if
you have money you have freedom you can
do whatever you want with your life you
can live wherever you want you can live
right next to your college if you want
so they you won't have to tr travel
three four hours a day so it's about
financial Independence you have to
become financially independent as soon
as possible what happened in the past is
gone there's no point in over about what
happened it's water under the bridge
what is important is what comes next you
have a whole life to
live so look what I would say is that
don't waste your time feeling sorry for
yourself about what happened in the
past think about what you have to do now
the most important thing is that you
need to become financially independent
then you'll be able to do whatever you
want live wherever you want have
whatever circle of friends you want and
so on you'll have colleagues and so on
so that's the most important thing for
you um so either you can pursuade your
parents to allow you to stay near the
college so you don't have to commute
three four hours a day that way you'll
have more time to spend with people in
your college Circle that way you will
have friends you will have conversations
you would't be lonely anymore and if
your parents are not willing to do that
then wait one more year or whatever I
you could take up a job part-time job if
that that can cover your expenses or you
wait a year or so until your college is
done you get your degree and then you
can take a proper job and have a whole
different life so you got to you know
problems are plenty in life everybody
has problems I understand what you're
facing I it's not easy it's not a joke
at all but you've got to be tough
mentally and you've got to find
Solutions workable
Solutions so for you I think the main
solution is find Financial Independence
which you don't have right now once you
have your
own income then you'll be in charge of
your life and you'll be able to turn
things around so please do that find a
way of doing that and all the best I
wish you the best do well in
life om prash says
please do a live stream only on problems
of life that teenagers face at least
once look I'll be happy to do that if
there is
a demand for
that I
mean I have been a teenager I haven't
forgotten what it was like to be a
teenager and did I have problems look
all teenagers have problems whatever
problems te teenagers face I also gone
through that and unlike other people who
have grown up I haven't forgotten what
it was like to be a teenager or a
kid so I certainly could will be happy
to do this if there is a demand for this
so maybe I'll put put up a poll on my
Community page of this Channel and I'll
ask if if there is a demand for that and
if enough people vote for it I I'll be
happy to do this so yeah so thank you
for the suggestion I I'll put up a poll
as soon as possible on the Community
page okay some questions from the live
stream let's do that I've already spoken
about the subash case I there's no point
repeating that um
I think trupti pel is saying yes about
that live about the problems of
teenagers live stream
okay uh himansu says update on
understanding America podcast any rough
date I announced in the first week of
November I said it'll be released next
week it's too late now okay I know I
said it will be released immediately I'm
working on that the first episode has
already been recorded and uh by the end
of this year a few more episodes will be
recorded and the first episode will be
released on this
channel in the first week of
December so that is a guarantee most
likely on the 2nd of December the first
episode of understanding America will
release and by the time I'll hopefully
have a bank of like four five episodes
so that you know there's less pressure
on me that's the only reason I haven't
released it thus far so yeah it's coming
it's already in process I'm already
putting out some shots on on the channel
in case you have seen
and yeah so it'll come out in the first
week of January which is in about what
less than two weeks from now that's when
the first episode will
release okay let's take some other
questions from the live chat before I go
back to questions from the
comments did I mean January I mean
January yes it will come out in the
first week of January probably January
2nd
Dam Kumar says I strongly disagree with
you on AI and coding so if you disagree
with me it will help if you tell me why
you disagree with me so we can have a
disagreement we can have a conversation
over that but I said I told you why I
think AI will will take over the entire
will will essentially
annihilate this job sector of
programming I told you why I think so so
if you disagree with me it helps if you
tell me why you disagree
otherwise we just shouting at each other
right I'm happy to have a
conversation about this but you have to
tell me why you disagree give me
specific reasons why you
disagree all right please do that and if
if you if you're going to do that then
hopefully I'll catch a comment because
there are so many comments on the live
chat that are coming up so
yeah
um Arian says will coalition government
politics slow India has progress
absolutely you need a single Power
Center in a government if you have a
coalition government where the main
power center depends on seven other
power power centers everybody has their
agenda then there's squabbling and
there's all kinds of friction and
inertia and that slows everything down
you can only have a common minimum
program and the word minimum is terrible
in this in this context so yes Coalition
politics is terrible for Any Nation
especially a nation that needs growth
like
India right I have spoken about starlink
multiple times so we will not go into
that once again Anita is saying first
week of Jan yes first week of Jan most
likely second of Jan for the
understanding America release of the
first episode okay let's go back to the
uh to the questions from the
comments okay that's a whole bunch of
questions photo he one Patel and normi
who the question is how did Europeans
solve the castism problem in Europe or
do Aristocrats of Europe Still Still
retain wealth and power and our no
Europe had a slavery system but the
descendants of the slaves and peasants
don't get any kind of reservation they
just have strict anti-discriminatory
laws in India we have all kinds of
reservation for what we call lower cast
but still we haven't been able to tackle
discrimination effectively and yet
despite not having reservations Europe
has been able to tackle discrimination
so effectively how do they do it okay
two kind of related questions first of
all there is no such thing as as cast
Okay in India we have had jati Verna
jati system the jati Verner system which
is a whole different thing from the soad
Del castas that the Portuguese and the
Spanish instituted in the Americas very
different and the same system exists in
Europe the jati Vera system historically
it
existed jati means lineages and this
Verna means the
occupations the Europeans also had that
I mean look at the the the cimes you
have among the Anglo-Saxon people the
English speaking people Hatcher Fletcher
Smith Aros Smith gold smith so on so
forth what is a thatcher a thater is an
occupation it's it's it's touching roofs
the process of touching you know putting
putting roofs on on houses and and
Cottages that's thatching so a person
who did that was called a thatcher and
that's a surname which means it was a
hereditary occupation what is Fletcher a
person who makes arrows to be used in
Warfare It's a Fletcher Keith Fletcher
was India's Cricket coach it's a surname
which means it's a hereditary occupation
Smith is a person who works with metal
that's one of the major cumes in in the
Anglo-Saxon world so you had hereditary
occupations everywhere in the world in
the Indo European world and other parts
of the world also and the same thing
existed in India but we call it
castism
and does the world have discrimination
of course there's discrimination
everywhere some and some of it is
terrible some of it may be called
discernment we'll not go into the
discernment part of that but what the
Europeans did is um in Europe what
happened is that they have
anti-discrimination laws and so on so
you're not allowed to discriminate
against a person based on things like
their their lineage their Heritage and
all
that and that is kind of and and those
laws are properly
implemented so that has solved any
problem of discrimination no one cares
today no one cares about the old
occupation
anymore uh the other question is do
arist Rats of Europe still retain wealth
and power some of them
do look the old nobility of France it is
a small minority segment of the
population but they still are some of
them are still wealthy and some of them
are still powerful and they still are a
powerful Lobby in French politics even
though they may not be so visible when
it comes to the British nobility they
still have wealth and
power the British royal family still is
extraordinarily
wealthy and the Lesser nobility also has
Estates and all that and they're able to
profit from
that and you still have monarchies in
many European nations right so there is
that uh in India we have done away with
that really genuinely done away with
that perhaps to our detriment perhaps
not only only time will tell us um you
had slavery in Europe of course I mean
do during the time of William the
Conqueror 1066 ad at least 10% of the
population of Britain was slaves they
used to wear copper collars which were
never taken off you will find skeletons
with copper collars around their necks
even
now the the copper collars were not
removed even in death so you had that
and you had the peasants who were almost
like slaves they had no land they used
to work on other people's land and they
were they used to live hand to mouth so
we you had a very feudal system in
Europe
with the majority of the population
being very
poor uh but yeah after the Industrial
Revolution a lot
changed so in India we never had slavery
we had the jati Verna system that today
we are told that it was a very
oppressive system which is a
lie uh and we have
reservations based on the jat not on the
jati system but the for cast system that
the British British imposed on India
which has actually created created a
cast system which we never
had uh and it has not solved any of
India's problems now people want more
and more reservations soon they will
want reservations in private sectors and
if that happens I think it's best to
leave India because then India will
never have Merit and the nation will
never progress so I hope it doesn't
happen uh so The Simple Solution is is
that a nation has to respect
Merit and that's what happened in Europe
right by abolishing all discrimination
and making everything based on Merit the
entire problem which may or may not have
existed was was was done away with and
in India also we can do away with it
this and this discrimination thing how
do you deal with discrimination if it
exists in India first thing in all
government certificates remove the word
cast if cast is not is to be abolished
as people say then why do we put cast on
the
certificates no government certificate
no academic marksheet or or or or
certificate should have the word
cast destroy cast
right I completely fully support
destroying
cast remove the word cast from all
certificates government certificates
educational certificates medical
certificates everything annihilate cast
completely
second make everything Merit based
whether it is admissions to schools
colleges universities whatever whether
it is jobs make everything Merit based
third give reservations based on
financial status to those who are below
poverty line or
whatever come up with a very simple
Criterion for those who need
reservations and give and what kind of
reservations are to be given free
education that's the kind of reservation
that should be given and then once you
are complet once you have completed your
free education you should be able to
compete only on
Merit that's it so if you do these
simple things in 20 30 years you can
solve all the problems in
India but then politicians won't get
votes right their votes are all based on
cast calculus and God knows what else
what other nonsense that's what keeps
India divided
and politicians benefit from the system
so they don't want to end the system
that's the
problem that is the problem the problem
is the
politicians they benefit from this they
benefit from the division that India the
divisions that these foreigners have
created in India so they will keep on
exacerbating these divisions and seeking
rent from these
divisions as a consequence of these
divisions they will never address the
problem that's the problem in India and
that's why India is not able to address
any of these long-standing issues of the
past 200 300
years so I hope that explains what the
problem
is okay God of asks me a question in
French that's the correct gramar so what
he's asking is that why is it that about
90% of political terms and words uh
originate in the French language why is
it so that's the question now is it true
that 90% of political terminology words
vocabulary Etc originates in the French
language I don't think it's
90% I think it's not entirely accurate
to say that 90% of all these terms come
from French now French definitely has
had a very significant influence on
political terminology
especially on
English political terminology okay and
other European languages also but even
other languages like Latin and Greek
have significantly influenced English
political terminology so um if you look
back historically what why French has
been influential on English on the
English language it all goes back to the
Norman conquest of England 1066 ad uh an
Invader who was called William the
bastard
okay he was the Duke of Normandy the
fourth or fifth descendant of Rollo the
Viking that guy invaded England he
became the last Foreigner to
successfully in invade and Conquer
England and he became from known as
William the Conqueror and as a
consequence of his conquest of England
Norman French became the language of the
ruling class in England for several
centuries and it has had a lasting it
has left a lasting impact on English
vocabulary
especially in governance and law and
administration all all that so the the
Modern English language is a Germanic
language originally it was it was
influenced by the Saxons and later by
the Normans both Germanic
peoples and Norman French was also a
Germanic based language then so so
that's the Norman Invasion thing okay
then you have the French Revolution late
18th century so the political ideas and
structures that came out of this
revolution introduced a bunch of terms
in political discourse in Europe and
eventually globally and some of these
terms that came out of this Revolution
were revolu sit which means citizen
Constitution which is Constitution
Republic which is Republic sovereignty
Liberty eality frity all these words
French words okay they all became
embedded in English eventually and then
for centuries French was the language of
diplomacy it was called the lingua
franka which means the French language
it was the language of diplomacy
international relations and it was the
language that was used in all courts in
Europe Royal courts in Europe and
because of this French terms like
Ambassador diplomacy
protocol and so on these French terms
came into widespread use across the
Diplomatic World okay so you had so many
such such French terms French origin
terms that that became widely used in uh
political terminology but you have
political terminology in the English
language that also draws from Latin and
Greek from the Latin language and the
Greek Lang language for example in the
US you have the Senate well the original
Senate was a Roman senate right um veto
was a Roman term legislature probably
was a Roman term so Latin term and from
the Greek language you have words like
democracy tyranny oligarchy plutocracy
blah blah blah all of that so um overall
political discourse has been influenced
by the French language to a large extent
and also by Latin and Greek I'm talking
about in the English language and in the
western world and you may have words
from other languages also so I wouldn't
say that 90% of the terminology comes
from French but a significant portion
certainly does come from
French yaj Noka says is it true that
ancient Egyptian monarchs practiced
sibling marriages between brothers and
sisters and produced children from there
from them what explains such degeneracy
were they inspired by stories of such
marriages among their gods in the
Egyptian mythology and some followers of
Semitic religions alleged that such
stories of incest are prevalent among
some of our Hindu gods too is that true
absolutely
untrue there is no such parallel among
the Hindu
gods absolutely none
okay there are no cousin marriages among
Hindu gods or or sibling marriages among
Hindu gods absolutely none now coming
back to the so that I hope that answers
the last question now coming back to the
first question it is indeed true that
Egyptian monarchs
pharaohs uh practiced sibling marriages
yeah it's a very weird thing because
historically no culture tolerates that
sort of ghastliness okay sibling
marriages uh some cultures have cousin
marriages which also produce all kinds
of genetic defects right um I mean
Pakistan has one of the highest
incidences of cousin marriages and
genetic defects which obviously go hand
inand so the Egyptian monarchs did have
this so in Egyptian mythology you have
the siblings Isis and Osiris they're
Gods right the gods and they are
siblings and they're married so the
Egyptian pharaohs the Egyptian rulers
they they they had
this first of all they had to show that
they were kind of divine not the same as
ordinary Mortals so they had to uh
behave like Isis and Osiris kind of so
they would have sibling marriages and
also the other factor that comes into
consideration is that they did not
want non-royal political part political
families to become prominent by through
through intermarriage so they wanted to
maintain purity of lineage which is like
weird but that's what what they did so
egyp eyptian Kings
would marry their sisters and produce
Offspring through them
but most Egyptian rulers had multiple
wives for example you have the very
famous example of Amen HP
III who ruled Egypt about two and a half
thousand
years three and a half thousand years
before today roughly three and a half
thousand years before today and he was
married to the daughter of the miani
King TPA he was also married to the
sister of the mitani king uh so the
mitani king
wasat Tata he was obviously of Indian
origin he spoke Sanskrit his sister was
gipa his daughter was thipa and both
were married to the Egyptian pharaoh
amep III and there is an extensive
correspondence between tarat and am thei
about various topics you know diplomatic
correspondence and after am the thir
died this this correspondence continues
between tar and
the uh Widow of amen theii and so on so
amen the thir we know he had multiple
wives one was his
sister and at least two of these Indian
origin princesses from the miani
Empire so it is possible that some of
the children that were born as a
consequence of this these sibling
marriages would have been genetically
deformed would have genetic defects but
they also married other non-related
people women from far away royal
families so that's the kind of practice
they
had so yeah it's one of the curious and
and
strange aspects of U Egyptian politics
but that's what it
was Vikram geopolitical says what's your
take on the cancer vaccine development
by Russia is it a final product or is it
still in development how will Russia
afford to provide its citizens with such
expensive vaccines for free which other
countries could get it so the Russian
government has announced that they have
developed a cancer vaccine and it's
going to be Avail made available for
free to all Russian
citizens now I don't know if it's a
final product or if it's in development
I would I would imagine that if it's in
development they would not announce it
or not distributed it's not distributed
yet I think it will be distributed in
2025 and made available to whoever needs
it so it that that kind of indicates
that it's a final product it's been
tested and it it's known to work I don't
know whether it it uh can prevent all
cancers or certain classes or categories
of of cancers but if they have actually
successfully done this then it's it's
groundbreaking for sure uh now the next
question is how will Russia afford to
provide its citizens with such expensive
vaccines we don't know if the vaccines
are expensive
I don't look most vaccines are can be
produced pretty cheaply especially if
you're producing the at scale like
millions or tens of millions or hundreds
of millions of doses I mean how was
India able to give away so many covid
vaccines for free to so many
countries India gave free covid vaccines
the covid vaccine doses millions of them
to various countries and India is not
super rich country or or at all right
but we were able to do it we could
afford it so if you produce vaccines at
scale at a real large scale it can
produce it pretty
inexpensively so I don't think it's
going to be a financial burden on the
Russian tax payer or the
government and I'm I'm if they have
actually successfully done this then I'm
think I think it's a good thing it's a
very nice thing that they are doing by
giving it for free to all U all their
citizens last question which other
countries will get it could get it I
expect friendly countries to Russia will
get
it so I suppose you could have
a an agreement between India and Russia
and perhaps India could be able to get
the vaccine perhaps or maybe produce it
in India or maybe pay for it whatever
we'll
see uh I'm sure they will not give the
vaccines to countries that are
antagonistic to them or countries who
want Russia broken up or dead right they
won't get the
vaccine um yeah so if it's true then
it's a it's a great step forward in
medicine right this is by baras F ma'am
I am not Indian but you people need a
formal supreme leader or King like
Britain or Iran they will treat Indians
as his children and not
voters and Indians will love him as a
father and not a ruler his presence will
be a source of courage and
unity yeah so this is something we used
to have when we had the imperial system
in India before the foreigners took over
before we we had democracy and
Constitution and all that we had rulers
right and Indian rulers their
constitution was Dharma the their their
um value system was the dharmic
values and they acted as father figures
for the population they were the father
of the entire Kingdom or or Empire or in
the case of the great Emperors of India
the whole the whole civilization
and they treated everyone as their
children as not and not as voters today
politicians will lie will lie to you for
votes but when something goes wrong in
your life they will not come to help you
when you had Kings in
India individual citizens could go and
appeal for help and they would be helped
so my question to my viewers is do you
agree with what this gentleman has to
say do you agree with what he says or
are we better off under this Democratic
constitutional secular socialist system
that we have in India today let me know
in the comments below or in the
chat okay this is a tremendously large
question gorov says we know India gain
independence 47 that Independence was
just a political was just political
Independence cultural Independence is
due yet we we will be fully independent
the day we abandon the British language
systems and administration structures I
agree when do you think people would
wake up and ask for cultural
Independence no people are not even
realizing that we need cultural and
civilizational Independence Indians are
very happy living their lives today
completely deracinated I live in Quebec
here that's in Canada uh every
Enterprise has to operate in French
every product should have French labels
and now after Bill 96 you have to talk
to your clients only in French on the
contrary in India you're thrown away
from the company if you don't speak the
language of your colonizers why don't we
Indians have this kind of love for our
language and culture we don't have this
love for our language and culture
because we have been der resonated for
years and years through our education
system our education system makes us
feel that our language our culture our
civilization our ancestors were inferior
backward and and Savages that's why we
don't have any love for our our language
and our culture we are not exposed to
our languages we don't know how to read
and write in our languages or if we do
it's just a burden because it's we have
to get we to pass the exams that's why
we learn it but we are not exposed to
our great literature in our indigenous
languages we are exposed to nothing so
because we are not aware of it we have
no love for it because we have no
exposure to it we have no love for it
and that's why we just don't care and at
the end of the day we are such a poor
nation that people are just trying to
survive people have to work 12 hours a
day to get a small salary and you you to
commute commute three or four hours a
day from your home to work and back home
and once you reach home all you can do
is
crash into your bed and go to sleep and
repeat the pro same cycle same process
next day so by keeping you completely
permanently occupied in the cycle of
misery they ensure that you can never
think of something
bigger that's what the system does to
you so it's it's a Confluence of all
these evils the evil education system
the poor standards that we have in India
today um the fact that India is still
such a poor country there's so much
corruption all of this conspires to come
together to ensure that we are being
further
colonized further mentally
colonized and the system benefits from
this the politicians benefit from the
system so they continue
it so um that's why we are in this the
state that we are in
today rajorshi says we we have big cats
amongst us why don't we have big
dogs oh okay let's let's go to our
friend Google shall we yeah we have big
cats among us no question about it we
are we in India know all the big cats
right let's see big cats so we in India
have so this is an example of a big cat
so which are the big
cats uh we have leopards in India yes we
do tigers in India yes lions in India
yes snow leopards in India yes cheetah
in India yes Jaguars we don't and the
Pumas and lynxes we don't but most of
the big cats we have them in India
including the Cal the caracal and
everybody all these various animals so
we have big cats we in India are very
familiar with big cats but what about
big dogs I'll tell you what there are
big dogs as well but we not so aware of
it for example the bear take a look at
what a bear looks like you see his face
her face whatever it's almost the same
as that of a dog so these guys the Bears
they you can can think of them as big
big dogs they are not part of the canine
family of of of species but they are
closely related to that and uh they can
even woof like dogs I mean if you if you
see
sloth
bear versus tiger and if you see the
video of this you will see the bear is
woofing just like a dog woof woof
barking so bears are like big dogs okay
and then you have seals so seals are
also closely related to dogs they are
like water dogs ocean dogs they also
Mark just like dogs and you have various
species of seeds like leopard seeds and
whatnot different species of seals so
they are also closely related to dogs so
are the
Dolphins okay the various Dolphins these
are also aquatic
members far away relatives of the dogs
and so are
whales so all these animals are in some
way or the other related to dogs but the
closest big closest to being big dogs is
the Bears and we have at least three or
four bear species in India we have the
black bear we have the brown bear which
lives which is found in the North in the
Himalayan region black bear brown bear
we have the sloth bear and we also have
another bear species that's found in
eastern India so these are big dogs and
I'll tell you what bears look look very
cute and fluffy and all that
cuddly but let me tell you if you see a
bear put as much distance as you can
between you yourself and the bear bears
are extremely powerful animals they can
be extremely violent extremely
aggressive and they can run way faster
than a human being tremendously fast
animals even though they look so clumsy
externally
so don't think a bear is is like a dog a
bear is like a dog but it's very
dangerous right
okay uh let's take some questions from
the live
chat um Mr rvsn says what's your opinion
on the future role of K Patel cash Patel
in the FBI so he has been nominated to
be the next boss of the FBI the next
director of the FBI probably he will
become the next director of the FBI
that's what Trump wants him to do
and as the next director of the FBI
he'll be a great American Patriot and do
whatever it takes to make the FBI even
more powerful and even more efficient
than before that's going to be his role
he is of he we know that he is of Indian
origin he's a Hindu but he's a US
citizen and he's going to serve his
Nation that's what is going to
happen
Okay uh prashi says I'm very curious
about crop circles around the world most
of them are unexplained what do you
think is crop circles is it made by
humans is it made by aliens what exactly
it is uh most intriguing was the
crabwood crop circle let's go to the
Google Maps uh Google Images so crop
circles be
became uh known in the 1970s and ' 80s
okay crop
circles so when I was a kid this used to
this started coming in the news
and this is initially it was just
circles but then later on the the the
figures the images the patterns became
more and more complex and now today you
have these things that are super complex
super complicated geometrical figures
some are not even circles
anymore and lots of hoaxers have been
caught humans who have been hoaxing this
thing who have been making crop circles
at night but it looks like some crop
circles are
not that easy to explain so most likely
I would say that most of these crop
circles are hoaxes they are done by
people but some it is claimed may not be
of human origin I am not sure of this
I'm a very skeptical
person
um so what do I think I think most of
them the vast majority of crop circles
okay let's see this crabwood crop circle
that he is talking about let's take a
look at that crabwood crop circle let me
see
crabwood crop
[Laughter]
circle okay okay okay okay that's the
that's the image it's an alien face with
some kind of uh pattern inside a
circle yeah so it's it's meant to look
like an alien face so what do I think I
think most of these are hoaxes I think
the the overwhelming majority of crop
circles are made by humans by people
just for fun I suppose or I mean what do
you gain from doing it you don't get any
money from doing it you know you can't
come forward and say that I made this
then the whole mystery and Intrigue
disappears so I think people do it just
for fun I suppose is it possible that
some of these are made by aliens well
you cannot discount the possibility
entirely I think I would say the pro
probability may be very low but yeah
let's keep an open mind and say that
maybe
maybe a tiny possibility that that
aliens may be behind this so I'm a very
skeptical person as hopefully you know I
think it's mostly hoaxes done by
humans okay let us
see say
frequently look I'm I'm I'm much better
in English Okay my upbringing my
childhood all of which all of that was
such that I did not have that much
exposure to Hindi uh I can write and
read Hindi I write reasonably well I am
very slow at reading hindii I can read a
whole page in English faster than than I
can read a sentence Hindi just because
of the way I the kind of upbringing I
had
okay so I am a prime example of mental
colonization anyway Hindi I don't think
it's our civilizational language our
civilization language is actually
Sanskrit and it's a language that even
few people fewer people know compared to
Hindi I mean Hindi so many people most
of us understand that so I'm more fluent
in English I express myself better in
English especially complex topics and
complex terminology scientific
terminology geopolitical terminology I
am way more comfortable doing that in
English and that's why I speak in
English am I lazy perhaps I'm lazy I
don't know say whatever you will so
that's why I prefer to do these live
streams in English and it also helps
that you know that way I can put forth
the Indian perspective to the rest of
the
world if I just speak in Hindi then the
rest of the world will never know what
our perspectives are or what my
perspective on our national interest in
these topics
is whether we like it or not today
English is the main language in the
world so if you want to put forth the
Indian
view then speak in English so for these
reasons I speak in in h in English
rather than
Hindi
right j25 says isn't India already in
the range of Pakistan's missiles for
example shahen 3 I'm not familiar with
the Gori gazi Shaheen whatever missile
categories they have but yes longest
range missile would probably have most
of India within its range yes I
agree geopolitical du says is bat
working quietly with North Korea and
should or will PM Modi ever visit North
Korea only PM Modi can answer the
question if we are doing something in
secret I would not know about
that so unfortunately I regretfully
cannot answer this question because I am
aware of only that information that's
available in the public domain
um
okay Amisha Mishra says what's beyond
the observable universe
so when we talk about the observable
universe we're talking about a subset of
the entire universe the entire universe
is
what what came into being as a
consequence of the um the phenomenon
that we call the Big Bang the very rapid
expansion of
SpaceTime and the observable universe is
a
sphere with us at the
center and the sphere has a diameter of
about 90 roughly 90 trillion light years
the so the radius is about 45 trillion
light years that's the observable
universe the universe is about 13.8
billion years old okay sorry not
trillion
billion the observable universe has a
diameter of 90 billion light years not
trillion so the observable so the age of
the universe is 13.8 billion
years and a light year is the distance
light can travel in one year so from
that perspective the observable universe
should have diameter of 13.8 * 2 is 27.6
billion light years but because the
universe has been expanding that's why
the observable universe has a diameter
of about 90 billion light years now the
question that Amisha is asking is what's
beyond the OB observ observable universe
what's beyond the observable universe is
much of what we see inside the
observable universe but it's just too
far for us to see
it and every single day every single
hour more galaxies are passing
beyond
the um the observable Horizon because of
the expansion of the universe so the
every single day the number of galaxies
that we can see in the universe is
decreasing because the universe is
expanding and the further away a galaxy
is from us the faster it is expand
expanding then eventually at a certain
point at a certain distance Beyond where
we are the expansion of the universe is
super luminal faster than the speed of
light without breaking the laws of
physics because it's the space time
itself that's expanding and not
something within it so beyond the
observable universe you have the
actual full Universe we don't know how
large it is we don't know the scale and
dimensions I mean Dimensions we know
four dimensions length bread he and time
but we don't know the scale of it we
don't even know if it's a circle or what
shape it is but we know it is the out
there and we will with the current
understand the current technology that
we have we will never be able to see
what's beyond beyond the observable
universe so what I can tell you is that
there's a much larger universe out there
beyond the observable universe but we
don't know how large it is that's all I
can
say right let's take some more
questions okay ronak Jen says why did
our ancestors accept the British French
the Portuguese in Dutch just after when
shivaji Maharaj liberated them from
genocidal regime of the Turks nobody
accepted
foreigners they conquered various parts
of India through
Force do you have any
choice of accepting or not when you've
got a sword hanging over your
neck these French Portuguese Dutch they
did not give you a choice would you
please accept us and then the Indians
accepted it's not that's not what
happened they took over territories by
force the French did horrible
attrocities wherever they ruled they
destroyed temples and built churches on
top of
them the Portuguese did horrific
atrocities in
Goa they burned people alive for
practicing Hinduism in secret they cut
hands of people and put them on a on a
on a pillar called the what hat stumb or
something which still exists
it was all done brutally through Force
there was no question of accepting or
not so we have the greatest sin in
geopolitics is weakness and that is what
we had we were suffering from and today
we should remember that the the greatest
sin is weakness don't be weak and
because we're weak we had to you know go
through all
that Ronnie rajput says what's the
current scenario about the UFOs in New
Jersey so yeah they're flying
around and uh no one knows what they
are and even the government isn't able
to explain what these things are so
right now yeah here's a question so the
government has no answers the military
has no answers these things are flying
around with
impunity uh some of these objects that
are visible are like orbs they look like
they're made of plasma some of them look
like regular drones some of them look
like aircraft so because we are in the
age of the
drones we don't know which which is a
drone which is a non- drone phenomenon
so right now the situation is that we
have no idea what that is if the
government of the US knows what it is
they're not telling anyone and yeah it's
it's kind of
um
perplexing wisdom Warrior says why are
Indians not into adventure
sports the uh per capita GDP in India is
$2500 the average person in India is
almost at a poverty line kind of thing
India is a very poor
country um if you earn 50,000 Rupees a
month you are in the top 5% I think of
the population in India if you earn more
than two lakh rupees a month you are in
the top
1% of
Indians so when you have a country
that's so poor where people simply
struggle to to have three meals a day
and and have a decent future for the
children do you think we'll have time
for ad adventure sports adventure sports
are expensive
you need all kinds of equipment let's
say we're talking about surfing a
surfboard can cost several laak rupees a
good quality surfboard if you don't have
a good quality surfboard it may break
when when you're up against big waves
what other adventure sports Paras
parasailing paragliding bunge jumping
all these are expensive sports even
tennis is an expensive sport even golf
is an expensive sport that's why Indians
don't do well in sports because of
poverty once India becomes a middle
income Nation with a per Capital GDP of
let's say $10,000 will be a whole
different beast and everybody will be
into all kinds of sporting activities
and all that main thing is you need to
have money to do all these activities
and India currently lacks
that okay kinki says I'm in the top 1%
awesome I want everybody to be in the
top
[Laughter]
1% okay
uh duaj says in your opinion what's what
government is better left wing or right
wing a go the right what is the best
form of best kind of government a
government that serves the nation and
its
people and furthers the national
interest and the civilizational and
cultural interest of the country now
whatever you Wing you want to assigned
to that kind of government I don't care
but that's the best government for any
country so I'm not talking about India
or Pakistan or whatever other country
for any country the right the best
government is the one that prioritizes
the long-term interests and prosperity
of the nation of the people of the
individuals and also the long-term
cultural continuity and cultural and
civilizational interest of the people
that's the the best government and
probably that's what we call right wing
unfortunately I don't care about his
left and right Wings they're all foreign
concept but yeah mclan says and this is
today's last question China bans exports
to the US of Gallum germanium Anon many
other key high-tech minerals how will
this impact the US the US will have to
find alternate sources China is China is
the exporter I mean China is home to
about 95% of these uh elements The Rare
Earth elements and all that
and the us will have to find alternate
sources for that I hear they have been
prospecting in their own territory they
they own a territory that's the size of
almost a continent and looks like they
have found
um found what they're looking for but it
will take time for them to be able to
extract it so the Americans will have to
find other sources for what they need so
these some of these elements are
critical in the te technology sector for
manufacturing and all that and the
Americans we have to find a solution to
that so yeah it can certainly impact
things in the US for some time at least
all right with that we are at the end of
today's session so many other questions
I can see that I'm very sorry I won't be
able to take
anymore but yeah let me end today's
session over here thank you so much for
all your questions for your viewership I
really appreciate that and I will see
you in next week's live stream in seven
days from now until then keep learning
keep asking questions and keep raising
your standards thank you very much take
care I'll see you soon bye